Suppose we have a list of part numbers or
假设有个零件编号或缩写列表
abbreviations that correspond to prices or descriptions,
对应的是价格或说明
we might have the short version in one table
我们可能在一个表格中有简短信息
but need to be able to look up more information elsewhere.
但是需要在其他地方查找更多信息
That's what Lookup up functions do.
Lookup 函数就是这个作用
They provide a way to use a keyword to look some other information up in a table.
它们使我们能够使用关键字在表格中查找其他信息
There are both horizontal and vertical lookup functions,
有水平和垂直查找函数
but we'll focus on just one, VLOOKUP.
但是我们将只讲解一种函数 VLOOKUP
I have a list of airport codes.
我有一个机场代码列表
Suppose I want to know which airport is code MCI.
假设我想知道哪个机场叫做 MCI
The leftmost column is the key and the second column in this case is the answer.
最左侧的列是键 第二列是答案
Scrolling down, I find out MCI is Kansas City.
向下滚动 发现 MCI 是堪萨斯城国际机场
The function that does this is VLOOKUP.
执行这一操作的函数是 VLOOKUP
I use =vlo, the value I'm looking up,
输入 =VLOOKUP 要查找的值
which is, ATL in this first case,
也就是 ATL
then the data range.
然后是数据区域
I'll select the two columns.
选择这两列
Then, the index of the column,
然后是列索引
which is the second.
即第二列
Now, I'm going to type false and close parentheses.
然后输入 false 和右括号
This worked great.
效果不错
I'll do it for the second destination as well.
第二个目的地也一样
I have the two columns,
选中这两列
and the second column is the answer,
第二列是答案
and false. Here we go.
输入 false 好了
Good. What if the airport code hadn't been in the list?
如果机场代码不在列表中呢
Let's try that. ZZZ is not in the list.
我们试试 ZZZ 它不在列表中
We get an error. We get an error because I put false
出现报错 这是因为我在公式中输入了 FALSE
in the formula to indicate I only want to find an exact match.
表明我只想完全匹配
What if I didn't put false in the formula?
如果没有在公式中输入 FALSE 呢？
Excel would return the closest match which for this problem is just wrong.
Excel 将返回最接近的匹配项 对这道题来说错了
A rule of thumb is,
一个规则是
that when looking up information with VLOOKUP,
使用 VLOOKUP 查找信息时
enter false in this optional parameter.
在此可选参数中输入 FALSE
Finding the wrong airport in this case is worse than getting an error.
找到错误的机场比出现报错更糟糕
Okay, one more thing.
还有一点
Instead of using columns as my range,
这里使用列作为区域
which did work just fine,
虽然也可行
it's really better practice to use a named range.
但是使用命名区域更好
It's more readable and less prone to errors.
更容易阅读并且不容易出错
I'll just name this one airport_lookup.
我将这个命名为 airport_lookup
And it works the same.
效果是一样的
I can even fill without worrying about losing my absolute address.
甚至可以填充到其他单元格 不用担心丢失绝对地址
Okay, your turn.
现在该你了